supply and demand trading is without a
doubt one of the best ways to do
technical analysis if you can understand
supply and demand you'll be able to take
some brilliant position so in this video
I'm going to teach you pretty much
everything that you need to know about
supply and demand so that you can start
getting insane results if you understand
the concept of supply and demand you
will have everything you need to carry
out profitable technical analysis I'm
going to give you absolutely everything
that you need to know from my 8 years of
experience so the first thing you need
to know is that markets are driven by by
buying and selling the whole reason that
markets move is because Traders are
buying and selling assets from one
another more importantly it's the
institutional Traders so in a market we
have two types of participants
institutions like commercial Banks hedge
funds central banks and Retail like me
and you individual Traders but us retail
Traders only make up a very small
percentage of the overall trading volume
so it's the institutional traders that
actually move the market so when these
institutional Traders are buying we see
the markets move up and when they're
selling we see the markets move down and
this happens because of supply and
demand if there is high demand for an
asset the supply gets bought up and then
the prices go up because the people that
hold the asset can demand more for the
transaction so if there's high demand
for an asset markets will move up when
there's low demand for an asset markets
will move down now to explain this in a
simple form let's say I've got 10 gold
coins and no one wants them no one's
interested in buying my 10 gold coins at
this point I'm going to have to sell the
them pretty cheap because otherwise I
won't sell them but let's say suddenly
something in the market changes and now
these gold coins are in high demand
while people will want to buy them off
me as fast as possible which means if I
want to I can up the price and people
will still pay for it and every time one
of these gold coins gets purchased and
is taken off the market the prices can
go up even more because the supply Falls
so high demand means low Supply and this
equates to high prices now imagine
someone else comes over with 100 more
gold coins now they're not so rare so
people might not be so interested in
buying them the supplies increased the
demand might fall therefore prices would
fall that is the basic theory of supply
and demand and this is pretty much
exactly what we see in the market now
supply and demand zones are plotted on
as consolidation areas before large
upward or downward movements and a
demand is simply a discounted price to
buy from while a supply is seen as a
premium price to sell out so to explain
that quickly if you bought something for
$100 and suddenly it was $150 you might
see $100 as a bargain so if the market
gets back down to that discounted $100
Mark you might buy more the same with
the premium price imagine the price of
that $100 purchase got to $200 well
that's a premium you might want to sell
there cuz you've doubled your money if
the market dips but then comes back to
that level it will be seen as a premium
so you may want to sell again and this
is exactly the kind of thing we see in
the market and how we aim to trade
supply and demand when a market pulls
back to a demand Zone we want to buy and
when the market pulls up to a supply
Zone we want to sell as I've just stated
supply and demand is visualized as zones
on a chart specifically consolidation
areas before large up or down moves but
there's a specific way to plot them
we'll get into real chart examples but
here it is so the common way to Mark out
supply and demand zones is to use the
last down candle before the up move for
a demand zone or the last up candle
before a down move for a supply zone now
I personally don't follow this
methodology I simply hadn't really heard
about this and I worked out my own way
to do it which I find works better for
me
and that is to use the last candle
before the impulse so an Impulse is a
large strong movement either up or down
in a market in this instance obviously
we are seeing the market as bullish the
market is pushing up so we have this
bullish impulse now the last candle
before the impulse is always going to be
some form of indecision candle with
Wicks either side and a smaller sideways
ranging body now if we consider what
this candle is actually showing us this
is where the significant buying has
taken place because this is the final
point before the market EXP exped to the
upside so by using this as our demand
Zone we're focusing on the prime area
where the mass buying really took place
now realistically you can choose
whichever one of these methods you like
back test them if you want but this is
how I do it the last candle before the
impulse now I'm going to show you what
it looks like and how we can plot these
zones on the charts so in this example
we have this large bearish impulsive
movement and above that we have this
sideways candle this indecision candle
so an indecision candle is defined as
such because it's showing indecision
it's not showing clear control from
buyers or from sellers this candle here
has got a large Wick above and a large
Wick below which means that buyers
attempted to go higher sellers attempted
to go lower but really it closes a
pretty indecisive candle compare that to
this one here where we have a huge
selling push with little to no wigs you
can see that clearly the sellers are in
control so this candle here at the top
is where in institutional selling
entered the market which makes this a
supply zone so we're using that last
candle before the impulse this is the
final point of which the sellers took
control of the market and this is where
those major sell orders were being
placed so the concept now would be that
because this was seen as a premium price
to sell from in the past if the market
is able to get back up into this Zone we
would be likely to see another push from
sellers if you'd sold your assets up
here at a high price and you have some
more where you wanted to short sell the
market well if it gets back up to here
again you see this as a premium you'd be
happy to get back in or get back out
depending whether you're looking to sell
more contracts or get out of your
existing position so if we play this
Market forward you see the market trades
up comes into this area of Supply
without breaking the high of the zone
and then we have a push to the downside
which would lead us into a new cell
trade opportunity now Supply zones are
always selling zones so Supply is always
the consolidation before a large
downward move and we always only want to
sell from these areas demand would be
the opposite so if we were in an uptrend
in this example instead of a downtrend
this consolidation before the upward
move would be a demand Zone and then the
focus would be on buying once the market
came into this level when we're trading
with the concept of supply and demand we
need to make sure we're always in line
with the trend so let's discuss that
just now so in this example we can see
the market is trending to the up side
we've got this low we have a lower high
we have a lower low but then we shift
into higher highs now because the market
has shifted into a higher high we would
anticipate a new higher low to form and
a continuation then into new higher
highs as we see this Market form if the
market is forming and printing higher
highs and higher lows we must only be
buying demand we must pretty much
completely ignore any Supply zones now
we can use Supply zones for targets but
we absolutely shouldn't be looking to
sell from Supply zones because we're
going to get beat down a lot of the time
so you can see that pretty much
everywhere in the market we are going to
see some form of supply and demand zones
so there's Supply Zone there Supply Zone
there we even get supply zones in these
smaller movements like we get one here
we're also going to get one here within
this trend but you can see that overall
because we're in an uptrend these are
rarely actually going to hold up and
work really well so what we want to do
is if the Market's printing higher highs
and higher lows we only want to focus on
buying demand okay so we would buy this
demand Zone and we would buy this demand
Zone too but we would absolutely not
sell from the supply zones because the
Market's trending up so we would be
going against the trend so we only buy
demand and uptrends Supply is not in our
focus and we would only sell Supply in
downtrends so if we flip the script here
and we have a market that's forming
lower lows and lower highs we would only
be looking to sell from Supply and we
would instead ignore all of the demand
zones that form within any of these
trending movements okay we wouldn't be
interested in buying this demand CU it's
not going to take us into new
considerable highs it's just likely to
end up in a loss we always need to
consider market efficiency and
imbalances when trading supply and
demand Concepts here's what I mean now
when it comes to validating your supply
and demand zones there's also one more
thing you need to be aware of obviously
we want to trade them with the trend but
we also need to consider Market
imbalances so take a look at these two
examples and you'll see they look very
similar except on this left example we
have a large Wick which is traded into
the demand area and then pushed away on
the right we don't have that Wick so
this price range here the impulsive
candle becomes an imbalance okay so in
the first example we have no imbalance
because the market has been retested the
demand has been retested before the
market pushed away meaning there's no
open price range or Gap left open on the
right we see the open price range is
left open and the demand Zone hasn't
been retested tested at all this means
that this is a valid demand Zone and
this is one we would buy from so we
never want to buy from demand zones that
have already been retested they're only
good one time but we do want to buy from
demand zones that haven't been retested
yet if we have an open imbalance demand
that will be a point that we want to buy
from remember that tip because it's very
important for making sure you don't buy
from redundant zones so now let's go to
a real chart and I'll show you how we
can mark up supply and demand in line
with the trending structure and the
efficiency and balances that we've
discussed and how we can use supply and
demand for entries and for Targets on
the positions that we take so now we're
looking at this 4-Hour price action on
gbpusd and we can see a market that has
just shifted from lower lows and lower
highs into a higher high with a break of
structure at this level so with the
market now breaking into new highs we
know this trend is bullish which means
we only want to buy we should not be
looking for selling opportunities here
which means we are going to be focused
on demand not supply So within this
bearish movement for example we've got a
supply Zone just here would we want to
focus on selling the supply absolutely
not we've got another Supply just here
but would we be interested in selling
this one also no and the reason why is
because this Market is clearly bullish
so selling Supply is actually pushing
against the trend going against the
direction of this market so what we
would want to do instead is buy from
demand now there's a a few areas of
demand in this trend that we would want
to keep in mind the first one really is
going to be around this area just here
so we can see when we had this break of
structure this was one of the candles
that actually kicked off this break and
there is some imbalance into this level
which can be visible just around this
area here now would we buy from this
area realistically no and the reason for
that is because we've also got deeper
imbalance down into the
extreme now the extreme zone is simply a
name we give to a zone that is the
furthest away from price so in this
price movement from this low up to this
High the extreme is going to be the
lowest Zone okay in that area it's going
to be this consolidation point so down
here we can see we had consolidation
before a large impulsive movement up now
this is a little bit trickier to Mark
the demand on but I'll show you a simple
tip now the last candle before the
impulse here is going to be this
indecision candle okay from the High to
the low it is that candle there now
because we have this large Wick
extending out of that what we can do is
actually just extend the demand down to
cover this low as well which means our
demand Zone would be this area here we
do that because we know as long as the
market doesn't push beneath this low we
should be viable and valid to go into a
new trending movement so because we have
the imbalance that we've mentioned just
previously this is going to be an area
we're interested in buying from we're
not interested in buying from any of
these other demand zones higher up
because there's no imbalance every
single time we get a demand we get a
push away a pull back and a retest okay
there is no imbalance until we reach
this point here yes there's a small
imbalance there but there's also deeper
imbalance at the extreme which makes
this the higher likelihood position for
us to take so now what we would want to
do is wait for the market to pull down
into this area of demand and then we
would look for our buying opportunity
let's move on to another opportunity as
to where we are right now then we can
see here that we had the low lower high
lower low lower high higher high and
then we've had this higher low form
which has been validated with this break
of structure so just here we've had a
new break which has pushed us into yet
again another phase of upside price
action this push drove us into this area
of Supply but do we want to trade this
Supply no because the market as of right
now is bullish so we will be continuing
to look for buying opportunities using
supply and demand Concepts in this
instance it's going to be demand so
let's move in and focus on this area of
price action then with where we are
right now where would be the optimal
buying zone for an opportunity or for a
trade to be taken well it's not going to
be this demand at the extreme because
this demand at the extreme has already
been retested just here it's also not
going to be that following demand
because that following demand has been
retested with a Weck there there and
there and yet again it's not going to be
this indecision candle before the the
large impulse away because this has been
retested here even if we were to refine
this candle down to this one this is
also been retested with a tap into the
Zone just there so there is no imbalance
anywhere lower down than pretty much
this point just here but we can see that
this demand is imbalance okay we've got
this large push away and this has left
an imbalance open which is likely to be
filled so because the imbalance is open
the probability of that becoming a
viable point to buy from has gone up a
pretty significant amount so what we
would want to now do is Mark on the last
candle before the impulse which is going
to be this dogee candle that we've got
marked out that is going to be our
demand Zone and now if we weigh up all
the factors we've discussed so far we've
got a demand Zone with an open imbalance
we have a clear uptrend and we have no
imbalance anywhere lower down in the
movement which makes this a high
probability point to take buys from so
if we wanted to get into this Market we
would be placing our buy here stop under
the zone and then we would Target higher
so now let's discuss using supply and
demand for entries and for targets well
the first thing is of course when we are
buying from demand we want to use buy
limits very very simple way to trade we
can place our buy limit on the demand
Zone and we can have stops under the
demand zone now for me I generally like
to have my stop losses under the next
significant point of structure just
because it makes it a little bit safer
so if we consider the structure here
we've got this higher high higher low
higher high higher low higher high High
higher low higher high and then we have
this higher low into a new high so
realistically this area just here is
going to be our next significant
structural point so if we put our stop
losses under this higher low that means
we are pretty much safe even if the
market decides to Wick through a little
bit and trade just underneath the demand
because that is sometimes going to
happen so this would be my preferable
trade stop loss is a little bit on the
larger side we are on the 4-Hour time
frame you could go with a tighter one
like this that is going to improve the
risk reward a fair amount but it will
also mean you will lose a few more
trades so it's just about balancing win
rates versus risk reward now supply and
demand can also be used in the
conflicting way to find Targets so what
we would do is actually identify a
supply Zone over to the left in the
trend that could be seen as a viable
level for the market to reach into now
in this example we've already retested
the supply that we just discussed here
so this Supply is out of the question
we're not interested in seeing the
market trade into that there is then no
open Supply zones until we reach this
point just here but here we've got a
pretty clear pretty viable Supply area
with imbalance so the imbalance is going
to be in this open price move here which
means this is a reasonably high
probability area for the market to reach
into so our trade could look like this
now we've used demand prot Trend with
the concept of imbalance to find our
entry for our trade and we've actually
then just gone and use Supply
conflicting against the trend as our
Target because we know if the Market's
bullish it's going to continue trading
up and if it continues trading up it's
going to continue to do that until
imbalances have been filled and Supply
zones have been retested so this is
going to act as really a magnet for
price to be drawn towards before any
meaningful reversal takes place so if
we're looking for buyers we can use that
magnet point for our trade targets and
for our profit taking so here's a great
example now of supply and demand used
for number one trade entries and number
two trade targets as you can see by
allowing that trade to play out as we
just did we saw the market come in
retest this demand area and then we had
a significant push in momentum coming in
just here the bullish momentum is
clearly indicated by these Wicks which
show rejections of selling pressure and
new strength from buyers we can then see
that the market pushed up and didn't
just push to this high but it actually
extended all the way through into that
Supply Zone that we just used for our
targets you can see as we said these are
magnet areas for price and markets are
unlikely to reverse significantly until
they reach areas of significant Supply
or demand so for a Buy trade even though
we're not looking to sell Supply we can
still use it as a clear Target because
it's the next meaningful point for any
reversal to potentially come underway so
this is our Target this is our entry
we've went with the safer conservative
stop on this point and that brought us a
5.47% return for 1% risk in a very
simple supply and demand setup now
there's one important important thing
you need to understand and that is the
concept of inducement or how to approach
multiple zones so we can see here that
having had this break of structure at
this level the Market's now shifted into
an uptrend we are looking to buy now
we've got two zones to pick from and in
the previous example just before we ran
over that I said the reason that we
would want to focus on this Zone the low
Zone over this one is because there is
still imbalance left open into this area
here now this concept that I'm
discussing I'm going to give you a bit
more clarity on now and it's this
concept that makes this top Zone an
inducement
zone so basically inducement is a bit of
a trap it's an area in the market that
looks like a good place to buy or sell
from but will realistically generally
land you in a loss so this area here is
an inducement cuz some Traders are going
to see this and think all right this is
a demand zone I'll buy from this Zone
but there's actually reason that the
market is going to be magnetized lower
now part of that is the imbalance that
we've already covered into this area of
consolidation in the low but there's
another aspect to this as well and it's
going to be
liquidity so to talk through liquidity
the first thing you need to know is that
the liquidity in question sits here okay
this line this is what we call equal low
liquidity now the reason it's equal lows
as you can see we've got one 2 3 equal
lows okay now when we see this this is
seen also as a support right support and
resistance conflicts with supply and
demand in a few different ways this is
one of them so with a support flow
Traders will be looking to buy the
market once it retests this level again
so if the market came down and hit this
level Traders would then look to buy
from that point now because we know
there's going to be a significant number
of retail buys there there's going to be
a significant number of retail stop
losses underneath that level okay
general education suggests when you buy
a support you put your stop- loss under
the low now this area of orders this
area of liquidity causes a problem for
buyers because we have this huge amount
of liquidity this huge amount of orders
and the markets react to orders it's
unlikely then that we're going to react
from this point and get a new solid
movement to the upside it's a lot more
likely that the market will be drawn
through into the area where the orders
are situated to then react from the
orders when the transactions are taking
place so this area here at the top the
one we first discussed this is an
inducement area because there's not real
massive reasons for the market to react
from this point there's still liquidity
in the market meaning these equal lows
there's still orders and transactions to
be filled underneath those equal lows
and then of course there's still the
imbalance into the demand Zone the
demand Zone obviously as we know is the
area where significant buying has taken
place before so it's seen as the
discount price level for the market to
react from again we know that Traders
like this price area for buying if the
market gets into here that's where
significant buying is going to take
place again it's not particularly going
to take place from the equal low
liquidity it's not going to take place
from the imbalance it's going to be from
the demand so we're looking for the
market to at least trade into this area
of demand for a new push to the upside
to take place which means we can ignore
this area up here which we would
classify as the inducement zone so
that's the inducement this is the true
Zone and this is the zone that we want
to take our buys from not the higher
area this same theory of inducement can
be used and seen a lot of times in the
market and I just want to make sure that
you're aware of it so that you can be
trading from the high probability points
like this one and not getting caught up
buying or selling from inducement zones
now there is a brilliant way that you
can use supply and demand to get better
entries and improve the risk versus
reward of the positions you take which
can double or triple your profits and
that is refining zones for this example
we're just going to Target the highs cuz
I really just want to draw Focus to the
entry here we would get a 7 0 7% or we
just call it 7.05% return on this trade
that is awesome very very good stuff if
we went for the more conservative entry
clearing that recent low we're looking
at a 4.5% potential from this trade at
1% risk which is also incredible however
we can refine the zone to improve the
risk reward more so this here is the
4-Hour demand okay this is a 4-Hour
chart that we're looking at and this is
a 4-Hour indecision candle if we go to
the hourly what we will now see is
within that 4-Hour dogee we've got
deeper imbalance and that brings us into
this area just here this smaller
indecision candle the last candle before
the impulse so now we've got new
imbalance just there which means that
this 4H hour Zone can be refined down to
a smaller 1hour Zone and you'll see that
this 1hour zone is actually about half
the size so if we were to bring the
entry down to the 1 hour point where we
get in leaving the stop loss exactly the
same still clearing that recent low if
we then go to the 4-Hour time frame
you'll see that we've just extended this
profit Target from
4.56% to
6.85% so we've added nearly another 2%
onto this trade without actually having
to do anything except for tightening the
entry and remember that 7.07% or 7.05%
more aggressive trade well that's now
going to be double we could get 14% out
of this trade simply by refining The
Zone because what we've done is half the
size of the entry we can half the size
of the stop loss and by halfing the stop
loss it means we can use double the
position size uh without risking any
more dollars okay so we could risk $100
here instead of $100 over a larger
amount by doubling the position size
which means the risk reward we're going
to get out of it we're going to make
double the profits on the movement just
with that small refinement so that right
there is the biggest trick that you can
use to improve your risk versus reward
simply refining zones to a time frame
relevant position now I want to mention
that is important as well see here we
went from the 4H hour to the hourly we
only want to be jumping like that we
don't want to go from the 4H hour to the
5m minute that's over refining that will
lead you to M trades but you could go
from the daily to the 4 Hour or from the
4 Hour to the hourly or from the hourly
to the 13 minute and so on and so on and
that is how you can maximize the profits
on your trades just like this one so
that's pretty much everything I wanted
to cover in this class I hope you've
enjoyed it if you have check out this
class next or click the link in the
description to check out my free course
which is going to teach you how to build
a trading system for yourself thank you
for watching and I'll see you in the
next video